Guide to the Margaret Fuller Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Margaret Fuller Papers
1832-1956
1872-1954
YCAL MSS 373
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.51
(37 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Connecticut-based author Margaret Witter Fuller (1872-1954).
Fuller, Margaret, 1872-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Margaret Fuller, circa 1950s.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Margaret Witter Fuller Papers, Archives & Special Collections, Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut.
Margaret Fuller (1872-1954)
Margaret Witter Fuller, born 23 January 1872 in Brooklyn, New York, was the daughter of Captain James Ebenezer Fuller and Rebecca Phillis (Hope) Fuller. In 1874, the family moved to Norwich, Connecticut, where Margaret Fuller resided for many years. A prolific writer, she authored poems, plays, and novels. Her published works include A New England Childhood (1916), Alma (1927), and The Complete History of the Deluge in Verse and Pictures (1936). Margaret Fuller died 1 February 1954 in Boston, Massachusetts.
Biographical information taken from Dodd Research Center description.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Connecticut-based author Margaret Witter Fuller (1872-1954). Correspondence contains letters with family, friends, most notably with poet and critic Edmund Clarence Stedman, and publishers. Writings includes drafts, notes, illustrations, and printed and other materials for novels, plays, poetry, and other writings, some of which appear to be unpublished. There are also photographs of Margaret Fuller, dating from early childhood to 1950, Fuller family, friends, places, and stage productions. The Photographs series features several cased photographs of Fuller's father and paternal grandfather, James Ebenezer Fuller and Ebenezer Fuller respectively. These photographs, which date circa the 1850s-1860s, include examples of early photographic processes, with ambrotypes, tintypes, and daguerrotypes, from New England area studios. Other materials in the collection include diaries, illustrations, notebooks, printed materials (annotated books), and miscellaneous manuscript material.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1846-1956. II. Writings, 1905-1953. III. Photographs, [1850s]-1952. IV. Personal Papers, 1832-1951.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Ambrotypes (photographs); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Tintypes (prints); Authors; Fuller, Ebenezer; Fuller, James Ebenezer; Fuller, Margaret, 1872-1954; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908
- Correspondence, 1846-1956; Series I; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains correspondence with family, friends, and publishers. The two largest groups of correspondents include members of the Fuller family and the poet and critic Edmund Clarence Stedman. Letters from Margaret Fuller, as well as some third-parties, are noted in parentheses in folder headings.
  Unsorted correspondence follows the alphabetical run of general correspondence. Additional correspondence can be found with the geneaological information and materials removed from printed items in Series III. Personal Papers.
  - "A" general, 1898-1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Bacheler, Christine, 1911-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Bacheler, Clementine, undated (Box 1)
  - Bacheler, Frances Hope, 1882-1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Bacheler, J. - Baker, G. B., 1913-1939, undated (Box 1)
  - Bard, Albert S., 1912-1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Bard, Charles - Bragg, Lillian, 1863-1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Brainerd, Eveline, 1907-1939, undated (Box 1)
  - Brainerd, Ira, 1908-1931; 2 (Box 1)
  - Branch, Anna H., 1905-1930 (Box 2)
  - Brandt, Carl, 1915-1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Briggs, Sallie Lee - Comstock, Daniel, 1903-1953 (Box 2)
  - "C" general, 1879-1956 (Box 2)
  - Cushman, Edwin - Dierkes Press, 1901-1952 (Box 2)
  - Dies, Laura Woodworth, 1881-1939 (Box 2)
  - Dodge - Dromgoole, Will Allen, 1905-1953, undated (Box 2)
  - Dubois, Egbert, 1868-1915 (Box 2)
  - DuChaillu, P. B. - Dyer, Frank L., 1884-1952 (Box 2)
  - Eastman, Charlotte Fuller (sister), 1902-1938, undated (Box 3)
  - Eastman, Col. Frank, 1898-1908 (Box 3)
  - Eastman, Mrs. Frank, 1901, undated (Box 3)
  - Eaton, Mary - Ellis, Carlyle, 1905-1917 (Box 3)
  - Ellsworth, William W., 1905-1935, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Elton, Ben - Franzen, 1898-1943, undated (Box 3)
  - French friends, 1914-1939 (Box 3)
  - Fuller family, 1858-1885, undated (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Alvan, 1902-1947 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Amalia, 1906 May 10 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Ebenezer (grandfather), 1863-1874, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Edward (brother), 1923-1954 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Flora Tufts, 1924-1928, undated (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Frank, 1932 August 3 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Harriet Louisa (grandmother), 1862 July 26 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Homer, 1953 January 16 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Hope Louise (sister), 1906-1929, undated (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Hubert B., 1951 July 27 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, J. F. C., undated (Box 4)
  - Fuller, James Ebenezer (father), 1859-1911 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, James E., 1912-1913 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Luther, 1908-1927 (Box 4)
  - Fuller, Lydia, 1944 September 27 (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to A - H), 1899-1956 (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to I - L), 1905-1955 (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to Charlotte Fuller Eastman), 1901-1939, undated (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to her sister H. Louise Fuller), 1892-1925, undated (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to her mother Rebecca Fuller), 1896-1908, undated (Box 5)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Letters to E. C. Stedman), 1898-1907, undated; 6 (Box 6)
  - Fuller, Martha, 1922, 1927 (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Mary, 1966 May 11 (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Peter, 1949 March 16 (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Rebecca Phillis Hope (mother), 1901-1916, undated (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Viola, 1944-1950, undated (Box 7)
  - Fuller, Walter, 1928, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Gale, Zona - Gilman, William C., 1904-1935, undated (Box 7)
  - Glasgow, Arthur Graham - Gould, George, 1902-1953, undated (Box 7)
  - Grahame, Elspeth - Henderson, 1898-1954, undated (Box 7)
  - Hidd. - Keeper, 1903-1953, undated (Box 7)
  - Kent, Harry Watson, 1902-1946 (Box 7)
  - Kingfisher, E. E. - Marshall, Edith, 1861-1952, undated (Box 8)
  - Marsland, Alice H., 1906-1924, undated (Box 8)
  - Martens, Johannes - Morley, Christopher, 1903-1951, undated (Box 8)
  - Morrow, Honore Willsie, 1914-1928 (Box 8)
  - Morrow, William, 1927-1931 (Box 8)
  - Mut. - Paterson, Isabel, 1905-1953 (Box 8)
  - Music Publishers, 1942-1953 (Box 8)
  - Penniman, James Hosmer, 1926-1931 (Box 9)
  - Penniman, Josiah - Robinson, T., 1902-1955 (Box 9)
  - Robinson, W. George, 1846-1946 (Box 9)
  - Sammons- Springfield Republican, 1903-1953 (Box 9)
  - Stedman, Arthur, 1899-1908 (Box 9)
  - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1891-1903; 2 (Box 9)
  - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1904-1908; 3 (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Edmund Clarence (Letters to Jonathan Trumbull), 1898-1907 (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Edmund Clarence (Undated letters, fragments, notes), 1889-1902, undated (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Ellen Douglas, 1904-1905 (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Fred, 1902 November 6 (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Laura H., 1899-1902 (Box 10)
  - Stedman, Dr. Thomas L. - Taylor, Marie, 1901-1955 (Box 10)
  - Teall, Edward N., 1918-1945 (Box 11)
  - Tew. - Torrence, Ridgely, 1902-1946 (Box 11)
  - Trask - Westa, 1894-1956 (Box 11)
  - Westminster Press, 1946-1951 (Box 11)
  - Wheelock, John Hall - Unidentified, 1910-1953, undated (Box 11)
  - Yantic Fire Engine Company, 1947 (Box 11)
  - Fragments in unknown hands, 1904, undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1863 (Box 11)
  - Unsorted correspondence, undated; 2 (Box 12)
- Writings, 1905-1953; Series II; 5; (12 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title or supplied heading.
  Series II, Writings, contains drafts, notes, illustrations, and printed and other materials for novels, plays, poetry, and other writings. There are drafts for published novels, such as The Golden Roof and One World At a Time, as well as apparently unpublished works, such as The North Parish. Unsorted writings follow the alphabetical list of titles.
  - Alma, 1922-1949, undated; 6 (Box 13)
  - Alma, undated (Box 14)
  - "Child It Is All So Simple", 1945 (Box 14)
  - "The Christmas Year", undated (Box 14)
  - The Complete History of the Deluge in Verse and Pictures, 1936, undated; 3 (Box 14)
  - The Complete History of the Deluge in Verse and Pictures, 1936, undated (Box 15)
  - "Connecticut's Mgt. Fuller", undated; 3 (Box 15)
  - "Connecticut's Mgt. Fuller", undated; 3 (Box 16)
  - "The Deaf Mute", undated (Box 16)
  - "The Dream", undated (Box 16)
  - "Dumas Entertains", 1941 (Box 16)
  - "The Fishing Season", 1941 (Box 16)
  - "Go It Little Towhead", 1941 November 6 (Box 16)
  - The Golden Roof, undated (Box 16)
  - "His Little Britisher", 1934, undated; 2 (Box 17)
  - "In the City of Hell", undated (Box 17)
  - "Jerusalem", undated (Box 17)
  - "Jimmie", undated (Box 17)
  - "The Little Thrush", undated (Box 17)
  - "The Mask", 1915-1936, undated; 4 (Box 17)
  - "The Mockingbird", undated (Box 17)
  - A New England Childhood, 1910-1912, undated; 2 (Box 18)
  - "The North Parish", 1905 (Box 18)
  - "The North Parish", 1905, undated; 2 (Box 19)
  - "One More Fling", undated (Box 19)
  - One World at a Time, undated (Box 19)
  - "The Out-Along Road", undated (Box 20)
  - "Overnight", 1937 November (Box 20)
  - [Poems], undated; 5 (Box 21)
  - "Posing in Paris", 1940 (Box 21)
  - "The Recent Mrs. Gilbert", 1951 October (Box 21)
  - "Roadway - Yantic, Connecticut", 1934 December 7 (Box 21)
  - "Robert Le Beau", 1934 (Box 22)
  - "The Season of Youth", 1923 (Box 22)
  - "The Things of the Morrow", undated (Box 22)
  - This Awakening, undated; 2 (Box 22)
  - "Towhead", 1928 (Box 22)
  - "Two of a Cast", undated; 2 (Box 23)
  - "Two Proselytes in Two Minutes", undated (Box 23)
  - "Water Babies", 1910 (Box 23)
  - "When It's Christmas Time", 1952-1953 (Box 23)
  - "The Witch Finders", 1931-1940; 5 (Box 23)
  - "Worthies of New England", undated; 2 (Box 23)
  - "Yantic Fire Engine Company", 1947 (Box 24)
  - Unsorted writings, undated; 12 (Box 24)
- Photographs, [1850s]-1952; Series III; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Series III, Photographs, contains photographs of Margaret Fuller, family, friends, places, and stage productions. There are photographs of Margaret Fuller from early childhood, circa 1870s, to 1950. The series features several cased photographs of Fuller's father and paternal grandfather, James Ebenezer Fuller and Ebenezer Fuller respectively. These photographs, which date circa the 1850s-1860s, include examples of early photographic processes, with ambrotypes, daguerrotypes, and tintypes, from New England area photographers.
  - Fuller, Margaret, [1870s]-1950, undated; 7 (Box 25)
  - Fuller, Ebenezer
  - Fuller, Edward (brother), undated (Box 25)
  - Fuller, Hope Louise (sister), 1869-1924, undated (Box 25)
  - Fuller, Hope Louise and Charlotte (sisters), 1903-1948, undated (Box 25)
  - Fuller, James Ebenezer (father), 1865, undated (Box 25)
  - Fuller, Rebecca Phillis Hope (mother), undated (Box 25)
  - Hope, Mary Newson (grandmother), undated (Box 25)
  - "Relatives", 1866-1920, undated; 2 (Box 25)
  - "Friends", 1892-1914, undated; 2 (Box 25)
  - One World at a Time, undated (Box 26)
  - Unidentified stage production, 1935, undated (Box 26)
  - Places, 1900-1952, undated; 3 (Box 26)
  - Unsorted photographs, 1865-1894, undated; 3 (Box 26)
  - Cased photographs
    - Fuller, Ebenezer, [circa 1858] (Box 27)
      Ambrotype, half-plate, in a leather-bound case, created by Webster & Bro., Louisville, Kentucky
    - Fuller, James Ebenezer, [circa 1858-1861]; 6 (Box 27)
      Includes:
      Daguerreotype, sixth-plate, in a leather-bound case
      Tintype, sixth-plate, in a leather-bound case
      Tintype, sixth-plate, in a thermoplastic case manufactured by The Holmes, Booth & Haydens Company
      Ambrotype, ninth-plate, in a thermoplastic case manufactured by Littlefield, Parsons, & Co.
      Ambrotype, quarter-plate, in a leather-bound case
      Ambrotype, ninth-plate, in a half-case, created by Benson C. Hazelton
- Personal Papers, 1832-1951, undated; Series IV; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Personal Papers, contains artwork and illustrations, some for writings, personal diaries and notebooks, financial records, printed materials, including several annotated books, and miscellaneous manuscript material removed from printed items.
  - Artwork and illustrations, undated; 4 (Box 28)
  - Diaries, 1832-1909; 4 (Box 28)
  - Geneaological information, 1905-1922, undated (Box 28)
  - Ledgers, 1944-1954; 2 (Box 29)
  - Manuscript record, 1934, undated (Box 29)
  - Material removed from printed items, undated; 16 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1875-1949, undated; 2 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous material, undated; 3 (Box 30)
  - Music compositions & songs, undated; 2 (Box 30)
  - Notebooks, 1948-1949, undated; 3 (Box 30)
  - Notebooks, undated; 5 (Box 31)
  - Printed material, 1893, undated; 2 (Box 31)
  - Printed material, 1903-1929, undated; 4 (Box 32)
  - Printed material, 1886-1951; 5 (Box 33)
  - Printed material, 1860-1948; 5 (Box 34)
  - Ribbon, undated (Box 34)
  - Scrapbooks, 1876 March 28 (Box 34)
  - Will, 1930 January 1 (Box 34)
- Oversize, 2.75; (3 boxes)
  - Artwork, illustrations, and miscellaneous material, undated (Box 35)
  - Scrapbook, 1936 January (Box 36)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 37)